Hello and welcome back to another
practice problem video. So for practice
problem videos, these are just going to
go straight to the point and do harder
problems that will help you either with
your chemistry homework or for the more
difficult problems help you prepare for
exams. In this particular video, we are
going to focus on the math skills to ACE
chemistry. So, we're going to be more
likely diving into things like for US to
metric conversions, which were not
covered previously in my other videos,
cubed volume conversions, which are very
commonly given in labs and in homeworks,
and we will do a multi-step conversion
showing how we do our thought process,
how units can guide you. I hope this
video helps. And let's go on to our
first example.
All right, let's start our first
example. So in this problem, we're going
to convert 25 ml to quartz. And if you
remember in my unit conversion video or
possibly in your handouts that you might
have the different US to metric
conversions available to you to try
different problems. So for this one, we
have to go from milliliters to quartz.
Meaning we have to try to bridge the gap
between those two systems. So when you
were looking for these tables, you need
to try to find either your given or your
desired units in them. So we started
with milliliters, which was one, and we
desire quartz. So when we go through
this and we go to volumes right over
here on the right hand side we can see
we have quartz right here and that's
linked to lers. So we have to bridge
that gap right we have liters to quartz
so we have to go from milliliters to
liters. So it's going to combine
multiple conversions. Keep in mind
depending on the conversion you use here
it could affect your significant
figures. meaning that we always have the
decimal number here. So you see the
1.057
that is four sigfigs. So if our original
number is five or greater, that means
that we'd have to round our final answer
to four sigfigs. But if your starting
number is 2, three, or four sigfigs, you
don't have to worry about it. So keep
that in mind. It might affect your
numbers. So let's try to do it. Convert
25 ml to quartz. Let's write down our
given and our and all of our pieces. So,
we have 25
milliliters.
We said before we had to go from
millilit to lers to quartz based on what
we discussed. So, we also have 1,000
milliliters
is 1 liter. And we can define that
conversion one of two ways. And then we
also have lers to quartz from our table
above. And that was 1.057
quartz is one liter. And we'll write
that down here in the corner. So that
was just from that that little chart. So
quartz and lers and I'm not blocking
that right now. Okay. So when we do
that, we start with our given which is
the 25 ml. And what we're going to do,
we're going to let the units guide your
thinking. Meaning your units need to be
opposite and cancel. So if you think
from before, right, we need to have it
where they are opposite. So we need
milliliters to all to be on the bottom
and on the top, right? So we see
milliliters on top, right? Now we need
it to be opposite to cancel. So
milliliters needs to be down here. So we
need to find which one has milliliters
on the bottom to lead to quartz. And
when we were looking at these, we can
see really quickly. All right. Well,
milliliters is right here. So, let's use
that one. So, we have 1,00 mls is one
liter. We know as a result, milliliters
cancel. So, that's what the highlighting
means that this is a cancel.
We now have to use our next step. So,
now we have liters on one side on top
and then uh so we need to put liters on
the bottom to cancel that one out. Now,
so when we do that next one, we got to
then choose out of our terms on the
other side and we see liter is on bottom
or the left hand conversion. So we will
now have liters there and then we will
put our quartz on top. When we do that,
we see lers cancels liters. Awesome. And
we are left with the unit that we want.
Now earlier I mentioned sigfigs doesn't
matter right now let's count. So our
first number we have 1 2 3 four sigfigs
and then on our court number we have
four sigfigs.
Now whenever we have a metric conversion
to metric they're exact. You do not have
to worry about it. So with one liter to
milliliters does not affect our
calculation. So we don't have to worry
about anything crazy. We just have to
make sure we round to four sigfigs for
this particular problem. So when we are
doing that right, we have we are going
to be doing the math here. So we have 25
times that 1.057
divided by 1,000. So when you go through
that what you are going to get is it's
going to be equal to 2.65 65
* 10 -2
quarts or you might have just have
gotten on your calculator 0
uh 0265
as your answer. And being that we want
to make sure that is in the correct
number of significant figures here, uh
we would have to put an extra zero at
the end here. So kind of made a little
mistake on my own on my own notes. So,
and that would be our final answer for
this particular problem. For our next
problem, we are going to go into a cubed
conversion problem, which is a very
common one on homeworks. So, let's get
to that one. This one's a harder one.
Now, why is that? So, I chose this one
on purpose as our last problem because
it is tough. And the whole idea of why
this makes it hard is because we are
dealing with cubed functions. There is
no straightforward
conversion between a cubed function
especially if you look on any of your
reference sheets you have length volumes
uh time but cubed is something that
doesn't quite come naturally and why is
that well let's think about this so it
says our what we are given is we have me
cubed
and then we desire
centime cubed And you might think like,
okay, well, can I just say that 1 m cub
is equal to 100 cm cubed? And the answer
is no. You you actually can't. So let me
prove to you why. So if we have let's
say a line and we say that this line is
5 m or let's even go simpler. Let's say
this line is 1 meter. All right. Well,
if I say that line is 1 m. Well, how
many centimeters is it? Well, it's 100
cm. That's the conversion. Great. Now,
what if I asked you, what about if I
square it? So, if I now make this a
squared function where I make the other
side 1 m with 100 cm.
Well, how do I find the square meters
here? Just like the square footage of
maybe your room that you're in. So, how
would you do that? Well, it's length
time width. So, if I do that, it will be
1 m * 1 m,
which is equal to me squared.
Or we show it as 100 cm
* 100 cm.
And that would be equal to 10,000
cm squared. Right? So when we show that
they are not equal, they're very much
different. And we just squared it. We
haven't even cubed it yet. So they're
very different. Let's now go one step
further.
If now if I take my
cube or sorry not my cube, my square
and now I want to
cube it.
For now we have some depth to it.
I'm best to be artistic here. Kind of
failing. So if we do that right, every
part is 1 meter and now every other
length is 100 cm.
We do the same math to find the volume,
right? But instead the volume
is length time width time height. Now,
so when we do that, we're going to see
that all right. All right. Well, if I do
1 m * 1 m * 1 m, this is going to be 1 m
cubed. And if I do the same thing for
centime, so 100 * 100 * 100,
this is now 1 million cm cubed, which is
very much different than what the other
option is. So when we were doing this
problem, this here on the bottom here is
our conversion factor. So 1 meter cubed
is 10 6 m cubed and we have to use that
for our problem. So this is something
I'd write down, right? So you don't have
to do that every time. But be aware that
you have that when it comes to cubes,
you have to derive it. And that's for
every cubed function. It's not just a
normal conversion. So going back to our
problem before, right? If I have 5 m
cubed,
we can cancel that out, right? Meaning
that we said that 1 m cubed was equal to
10 6 cm cubed.
And we can now see that me cubed cancels
me cubed. And let me uh rewrite this. So
we'll show me cancels meters and the
cubes cancel. So just to kind of
illustrate they need to actually cancel.
So what this makes our final answer to
be is 5 * 10
or 5.0
* 10 6 cm cubed.
That is our answer. Right? So that was a
lot of work for one little problem. All
right. So for this problem we are going
to do a multi-step conversion. This is
pretty as close as you can get to an
official dimensional analysis problem.
It just took out the word problem part.
So what this one says is we want to
convert 32.5 m hour to centime per
millisecond. So we have to do a top and
bottom conversion. So with this let's
write down what is given. So we have
32.5
miles per hour and we need to convert
miles to centimeters and hours to
milliseconds.
So when you are doing these the first
key or first tip is do one conversion at
a time. Meaning that when you kind of
look at these, you have distance on top
and time on the bottom.
You want to either do distance, all
distance until you get to your final
unit or do all time until you get to
your to your final unit. So do one
conversion at a time. So let's set this
up. So, and it would be really helpful
if you have any of your little unit
sheets. So, that way you can try to see
how you how you can find those
conversions. One of the hardest parts is
just setting up the problem finding the
conversions. So, we have our 32.5 miles
that will be over an hour. So, that's 1
hour, right? So, mph miles per hour if
you think of your speedometer. So, let's
first start with let's do miles first.
So with this one, the first thing is is
all right. Well, how many let's try to
think of a way how to get the
centimeters. Well, if we try to map it
out for ourselves, we can go from miles,
we can go to feet,
we can go to inches, and then to
centimeters. So we can do three steps,
which is a long one, but at least it
helps show our process, which is
important. So, all right. If we have one
mile, how many feet are in a mile? Well,
look on your sheet, right? Or you can do
a little Google search. Either way, when
you look that up, you see there would be
5,280
ft in 1 mile. Miles cancels.
Now, for feet into inches, well, for
every 1 ft, there are 12 in. So, 1 ft
cancels feet, right? Let the units guide
you. We can see that they will cancel.
Now we do our next step which is
centime. So for centimeters, oops, this
is the wrong one. So for centimeters
we have it's 1 in is 2.54 cm.
So one thing you always notice is that
the smaller unit tends to have more and
then the bigger unit is always one to
make it simple, right? Make it easier.
But let those units push you to how to
cancel. Okay, so we now have it in
centimeters. So great, that is one of
our units. One down. Now we got to do
milliseconds. So we start with hours.
This one should be simple, right? You
probably look at the clock every single
day of your life, right? You can tell
time. So if we do the first one, well,
let's map it out again. So if we would
want to go from hours to minutes to
seconds to milliseconds.
So we have 1 hour is 60 minutes
and you can continue the calculation
down the lane. They don't have to be uh
one after another. So keep that in mind.
So hour cancels hour. So notice how far
apart of the problem they are, but they
still cancel, right? they're still
opposite of each other. Even though it's
four steps down, they still cancel.
So, and then we'll have um we need to
cancel minutes next. So, we have for
every 1 minute is 60 seconds. And then
we can try to highlight that. So, we
have minutes cancel.
And now for seconds.
So, for every 1 second, we have 1,000
milliseconds, which is our very last
part. And let's get a color that I have
not used. We use blue. The seconds
cancel. And now we're looking for
milliseconds. Look how crazy long this
is. There's 1 2 3 4 5 six steps for this
problem. But the one thing is noticing
the units are cancelling, right? So, you
can see even the hours cancel each
other. here. And I'm going to just put
like a maybe kind of illustrate that
with a line. Right? You can kind of see
how far apart those are. The miles
cancel each other, the feet cancel, the
inches cancel, the minutes cancel, the
seconds cancel. So now you got to solve
it. Put in your calculator. That's the
tough part. So the way to put this in
your calculator is you would say you
would, if you follow along, is you
multiply the top parts. So, it's 32.5
* 5,280
* 12 * 2.54
* 1 * 1 * 1. Okay, so you hit equals on
that. Then what you're going to do is
divide by 60, hit equal, divide by 60,
hit equal, and then divide by a,000. So
do one step at a time because your
calculator will follow it. And make sure
that while you're going through it, you
are entering the correct values. It's
really easy to accidentally mess up a
value. Okay. And the other thing is we
will have how many sigfigs here? Um, so
we have three sigfigs.
This is all within US units. So that's
exact. This is US to US exact. This one,
even though it's metric to inches, this
is the one exact conversion there is
between US to metric. And all the rest
are exact. So they don't affect it. So
we'll have three of them. So when you
solve this, you should get 1.45
cm per millisecond is your final answer.
Okay? And that's how you solve a
multi-step conversion. We there will be
more in other videos. So if you go to my
dimensional analysis video um which this
video will come up before that one, but
it probably maybe by the time you're
viewing this, it will already be out. So
look for that in my math skills to ACE
chemistry playlist. if you need any help
with your math so that way you can
practice them. Okay, then thank you so
much. I hope this video helps you.
[Music]